<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-atom-crosspost-00" ipr="none">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="AtomCrossPost">Atom Cross-posting Extensions</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
      <organization>Six Apart Ltd.</organization>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="August" year="2009" />

    <abstract>
      <t>In order to increase content visibility, many publishers are now
      duplicating their content or a summary thereof on other sites. This
      document describes an extension to the Atom syndication format for
      declaring such duplicates such that feed consumers which see both may
      detect this usage.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In order to increase content visibility, many publishers are now
      duplicating their content or a summary thereof on other sites. This
      document describes an extension to the Atom syndication format for
      declaring such duplicates such that feed consumers which see both may
      detect this usage.</t>

      <t>This specification assumes that there is a single, "primary" version
      of an entry created by an origin publisher and zero or more secondary
      duplicates. It is also assumed that the origin publisher is in control
      of the creation of such duplicates and is therefore in a position to
      document them as part of the Atom description of the primary version. A
      mechanism is also provided to mark the secondary duplicates as such, but
      it is acknowledged that in many cases the publisher of such secondary
      duplicates does not have the information required to create such a
      reference.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extension Namespace">
      <t>The extension elements described in this specification are in the
      namespace identified by the URI <spanx style="verb">http://purl.org/syndication/cross-posting</spanx>.
      In this specification, the prefix <spanx style="verb">crosspost:</spanx>
      is used to represent this namespace, though this is just a notational
      convention; any valid prefix may be used as described by the XML
      Namespaces specification. The prefix <spanx style="verb">atom:</spanx>
      is used to represent the Atom namespace as defined in the Atom 1.0
      specification.</t>

      <t>TODO: Reference the Atom spec.</t>

      <t>TODO: Reference the namespaces spec.</t>

      <t>TODO: Actually register that namespace URI.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The crosspost:target extension element">
      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx> extension element,
      when used as a direct child of an <spanx style="verb">atom:entry</spanx>
      element, indicates that the corresponding entry is a primary version and
      that the entry described by its attributes is a secondary duplicate.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx> element MUST contain
      zero or one <spanx style="verb">atom:id</spanx> elements whose value
      matches the <spanx style="verb">atom:id</spanx> element of the entry
      representing the secondary duplicate as published in this or another
      feed.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx> element MAY contain
      one or more <spanx style="verb">atom:link</spanx> elements as defined by
      the Atom specification to give the consumer a hint as to where a
      representation of the secondary duplicate may be found.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx> element MAY contain
      one <spanx style="verb">atom:source</spanx> element as defined by the
      Atom specification which describes the feed in which the entry
      representing the secondary duplicate may be found.</t>

      <t>A single Atom entry may contain zero or more <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx>
      elements, each describing a distinct secondary duplicate.</t>

      <t>A feed publisher that has knowingly created one or more secondary
      duplicates SHOULD reference each one within the entry representing the
      primary version using the <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx>
      element.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The crosspost:source extension element">
      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> extension element,
      when used as a direct child of an <spanx style="verb">atom:entry</spanx>
      element, indicates that the corresponding entry is a secondary duplicate
      and that the entry described by its attributes is the corresponding
      primary version. This element SHOULD be used when an entry is published
      that is known to the feed publisher to be a secondary duplicate.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> element MUST contain
      zero or one <spanx style="verb">atom:id</spanx> elements whose value
      matches the <spanx style="verb">atom:id</spanx> element of the entry
      representing the primary version as published in this or another
      feed.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> element MAY contain
      one or more <spanx style="verb">atom:link</spanx> elements as defined by
      the Atom specification to give the consumer a hint as to where a
      representation of the primary version may be found.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> element MAY contain
      one <spanx style="verb">atom:source</spanx> element as defined by the
      Atom specification which describes the feed in which the entry
      representing the primary version may be found.</t>

      <t>A single Atom entry may contain zero or one <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx>
      elements.</t>

      <t>The absense of this element does not necessarily indicate that an
      entry is not a secondary duplicate; in many cases a feed publisher will
      not know whether a given entry is a secondary duplicate and will thus
      omit this attribute in all cases. How a feed publisher determines that a
      given entry is a secondary duplicate is not defined by this
      specification.</t>

      <t>A feed publisher that is both publishing a secondary duplicate and
      knowingly creating one or more tertiary duplicates (that is, duplicates
      of a duplicate itself) SHOULD publish both <spanx style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx>
      and <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> elements indicating the
      ancestry of the content. However, creating tertiary duplicates is NOT
      RECOMMENDED.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use in RSS">
      <t>This extension MAY also be used with feeds in RSS format.</t>

      <t>The <spanx style="verb">crosspost:source</spanx> and <spanx
      style="verb">crosspost:target</spanx> elements MAY be used within RSS
      feeds as children of the "item" element. When used in this way, their
      relationship with the "item" element is the same as with the atom:entry
      element as described above, and their child elements MUST still be the
      Atom elements defined above, in the Atom XML namespace.</t>

      <t>The RSS "guid" element SHOULD be considered equivalent to the atom:id
      element when used as a child of the RSS "item" element.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This specification defines attributes that allow content in one
      resource to make assertions about content in another resource. Consumers
      MUST NOT consider such assertions to be authoritative without additional
      information that can be used to verify the validity of the assertion.
      For example, if a consumer may allow such cross-resource assertions if
      both resources are known -- by some means outside of the scope of this
      specification -- to be published by the same author.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <section title="Examples">
      <t>This appendix is non-normative</t>

      <section title="Entry representing Primary Version">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[<entry>
    <id>tag:blogtastic.example.com,2009:5a12451543</id>
    <title>Photos from my Weekend</title>
    <link href="http://blogtastic.example.com/5a12451543" />
    <!-- (other standard Atom elements elided for brevity) -->
    <crosspost:target>
        <id>tag:jibber.example.org,2005:4523452</id>
        <source>
            <link rel="self"
                  type="application/atom+xml"
                  href="http://jibber.example.org/geraldine.atom" />
        </source>
    </crosspost:target>
</entry>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Entry representing a Secondary Duplicate">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[<entry>
    <id>tag:jibber.example.org,2005:4523452</id>
    <title>geraldine: Photos from my Weekend
               http://sillyurl.example.net/abc123</title>
    <link href="http://jibber.example.net/statuses/4523452" />
    <!-- (other standard Atom elements elided for brevity) -->
    <crosspost:source>
        <id>tag:blogtastic.example.com,2009:5a12451543</id>
    </crosspost:source>
</entry>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
